Guide to the Adam Peiperl collection, 2000-2010 MS2248
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Adam Peiperl collection
2000-2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Peiperl, Adam
MS2248
0.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains photomontages, both printed photographs and a cd of the images, of dancers and GWU dance students by artist Adam Peiperl and a DVD of his sheet sculptures in polarized light.
Box 1
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Adam Peiperl, 2008 (Accession 2008.021)
Historical or Biographical Note
Adam Peiperl (June 4, 1935- ) has spent more than three decades incorporating technology in his artwork. He is a kinetic light sculptor, photographer and videographer. He has created sculptures by using polarized light and also has used digital technology to create his art. He earned a BS in Chemistry from GWU in 1957. His photomontages combine his longtime passions, art and photography. He has had one-man shows at the Baltimore Museum of Art, Smithsonian National Museum of History and Technology, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, and Philadelphia Art Alliance. In addition, his work has often appeared in group shows and is in the permanent collections of the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Smithsonian National Museum of American History, Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, Fred Jones Jr. Museum of Art of the University of Oklahoma, Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen (Rotterdam), and Kreeger Museum.
In addition to his status as a graduate of GWU, his connection to the University comes through his collaboration with choreographer Maida Withers, a prominent faculty member in the GWU Dance Program since 1966. He has worked closely with Ms. Withers and her Dance Construction Company. He has been photographing GWU dance students since 1986.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of examples of Adam Peiperl's photomontages, images, CDs, and a DVD titled "Sheet Sculptures in Polarized Light," consisting of video renditions of his sculptures rotating and displaying iridescent colors of the spectrum. There is also one poster for the Senior Thesis Dance Concert at George Washington University on March 28, 2001. The poster design and photography were done by Adam Peiperl. Mr. Peiperl described these works as the choreography of Maida Withers in snapshots. The images in box three were taken by Mr. Peiperl of performances of choreographic thesis work "The Trials of Terpsichore," by GW graduating senior Courtney Coughlin. The background of these images are digital compositions by Mr. Peiperl. For many of the images found throughout the collection the titles were taken from the file title supplied by Mr. Peiperl. At times the title is clearly missing data and in those cases the data has been inserted in brackets.
Collection Organization
This collection does not have series. The images are in the order created by the Donor.
Washington (D.C.); Color photographs; Dance; Peiperl, Adam; George Washington University. Dept. of Theater and Dance
- Alexis Major in Adam Peiperl's kaleidoscope interior image, 11/2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) entering columns, May, 05/2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) (2) on columns, July 2001, 07/02/2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) on mast with flag, July 2001, 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) on black with Adam Pei [perl kaleidoscope interior image], 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) with kaleidoscope interior image and [columns], 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) in columns, July 2001, 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- El Naar Haninah (Jo Elle Johnson) (2) on space road, Ju[ly 2001], 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Alexis Major with Adam Peiperl's four rings, March 2001, 03/2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Alexis Major in Sackler Gallery, March 2001, 03/2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Joseph Mills on Adam Peiperl's space roads, Aug 2001, 08/2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Colleen Hooper with Adam Peiperl's Guardians, Sep 2001, 09/2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Colleen Hooper with Modigliani's Head of a Woman at the National Gallery of Art, 04/2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Limar (Liliana Cuervo) with Adam Peiperl's Light Core, 07/2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Sasha Kukin and Iwona Olszowska with Adam Peiperl's Gua[rdians], 02/2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Joseph Mills with Adam Peiperl's Guardians, 08/2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Kerry Joyce (3) with Adam Peiperl's three ovals in space, 02/2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Kerry Joyce with Adam Peiperl's Light Core, Oct 2001, 10/2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Kerry on three stones, Oct 2001 [Kerry Joyce], 10/2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Kerry Joyce with church door, Nov 2001, 11/2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Kerry Joyce on hematite, Oct 2001, 10/2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Kerry Joyce with Adam Peiperl's Hole in the Sky, Oct 2001, 10/2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Kerry Joyce on Cloud, Dec 2001, 12/2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Daniela Wancier in Adam Peiperl's parallelograms, April [2003], 04/2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Kerry Joyce and Deidre MacDiarmid with Adam Peiperl's ziggurat, 03/2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- CD with digital images of photomontages in the collection (Box 1, Folder 26, Cassette 1)
  General note
  The CD has a handwritten note "Adam Peiperl Dance Photomontages"
- Sheet Sculptures in Polarized Light [DVD] (Box 1, Folder 27, Dvd 1)
  The DVD includes: 1. Hole in the Sky, 2. Mantle, 3. Sails and Pyramids, 4. Obelisks, 5. Origin, 6. Arches, 7. Guardians
- Senior Thesis Dance Concert, 03/28/2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  On the CD this is the 26th image.
- Molly Berger 1 in Skyway, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Molly Berger 2 in Skyway, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Molly Berger 1 in Ziggurat, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Christina Holvas in Skyway, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ricci Poorman in Skyway, 2010 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Five dance photomontages, 2010 May (Box 3, Cd 1)
- Press release, 2010 May 26 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Department of Theater and Dance "Courtney Coughlin Honors Thesis photos taken by GW alum, Adam Peiperl. http://gwutrda.blogspot.com/2010/05/courtney-couglin-honors-thesis-photos.html